(text softly clacking)
(suspenseful music)
(suspenseful music drowns out speaker)
(bushes rustling)
(videographer breathing)
- [Gregor] They're just everywhere.
Whoa, this is really blue.
You should come look, this is so blue.
- [Researcher] Look at
how many you're finding.
- [Gregor] I feel
like Gollum, my precious!
if it weren't so dangerous,
it'd be a fun activity to do.
- [Researcher] These are the big chunks,
so what about all the
particles you can't see?
- This same kind of material
was used in the construction
of the World Trade Center buildings.
And when the towers fell,
it was pulverized to microscopic size
and released into the air.
The particles remained airborne for days
and thousands of people
unknowingly breathed them in.
They buried themselves
deep within people's lungs,
wreaking havoc and causing
all sorts of diseases.
We've known for decades
that these particles
are extremely dangerous,
but when the towers
fell, no one was warned.
- The concentrations are such
that they don't pose a health hazard.
- [Gregor] And yet today the
diseases linked to that dust
have killed more than twice as many people
as the attacks themselves.
Once we started looking,
we kept finding this material
in places we never expected.
- He was telling the newspapers,
"People aren't just eating it
and breathing it, they're mainlining it."
- [Gregor] In popular
off-roading spots, in makeup,
and even kids toys.
- [Sean] Say It Ain't
So Mickey Mouse crayons.
- No!
It's been detected in the dust
around schools and homes.
- Five generations of
people died up there.
- [Gregor] And instead
of banning it outright,
we let it spread.
(camera shutter clicking)
Some countries are still
importing hundreds of thousands
of tons each year,
and it's estimated that by 2035,
nearly 2.8 million people
might die because of it.
(dramatic music)
This is a video about a
deadly miracle material
we can't stop using.
This investigation is based
on publicly available
documents, recordings,
and third party sources.
All of our links are in the description.
Thank you to Ground News
for sponsoring this video.
More about them later.
There is this story
about the ancient Greeks
from around the second century AD.
They had this golden lantern
that would burn for a whole
year without going out,
all because of a very special wick
that just wouldn't burn down.
So how did they develop this technology?
Well, the truth is they
didn't, they found it.
Imagine you're walking
around 2,000 years ago
and you see this fluffy looking
stuff poking out the ground.
It's got all of these fibers
that you can pull apart
and twist into shapes.
- [Sean] First off,
let's get a nice bundle.
So it looks like cotton.
- [Gregor] It looks like
it would burn really well,
like it would just-
- Yeah,
you can start a fire
with it, right, alright.
- [Gregor] Okay, let's see what happens.
- [Sean] It's not burning.
- That's because this is actually a rock.
It's a naturally occurring mineral.
The core building block is simple.
It's a silicon atom surrounded
by four oxygen atoms.
Now silicon has four
electrons in its outer shell,
but it really wants eight.
So each of the oxygens
shares one electron with it,
but oxygen doesn't share evenly
since it's more
electronegative than silicon,
it pulls those shared
electrons closer to itself.
This leaves the oxygen
side slightly negative
and the silicon side slightly positive.
Now there's an electrostatic
attraction between these atoms,
which pulls the atoms closer together
and strengthens this bond.
The result is an incredibly
stable pyramid shaped unit
called as silica tetrahedron.
But if you look at the
oxygens in these corner spots,
they've only shared one electron,
but they actually want two to
complete their outer shells.
So the corners link up
with other silicon atoms
to form more tetrahedra.
And in this way, the
structure just keeps growing.
The bonds inside here are
incredibly strong and stable,
and because the atoms
are already tightly bound
to the oxygens inside
the silicate structure,
the oxygen in the air has
nothing to react with,
so the material doesn't burn.
But overall, there's nothing special
about these building blocks.
More than 90% of the Earth's minerals
are made from this stuff,
everything from quartz to clay.
What makes this material special is
how those units link up.
Here, the tetrahedra have formed a sheet,
and bonded to it there is
actually a second sheet
made of magnesium atoms
and hydroxyl groups,
which are just an oxygen
and a hydrogen stuck together.
Now, the atomic spacings
of these two layers
are slightly different.
So there's a tiny mismatch,
which causes tension
between these layers
causing them to curl up,
and you end up with these
tiny scroll-like tubes.
These tubes don't break
down easily under heat.
The structure stays stable up
to around 600 degrees Celsius.
So like all these individual fibers
that you see running through here,
those are all like these curls?
- Yes.
- What is that, what was that there?
- [Sean] That's just a place
where I twisted the
fiber with my tweezers.
- Oh, okay.
And when you twist these fibers,
they actually don't break.
So it's literally a rock you can weave.
And when you do,
the fibers form a tangled,
layered structure.
So if heat is introduced,
it has to pass from fiber
to fiber across many contact points
with air filling the spaces between them.
This reduces how quickly heat can spread
through the material.
Because of that, people
started weaving it into things
like theater curtains
and insulation blankets for steam engines,
even fireproof clothing,
essentially anywhere
they didn't want something to catch fire.
But by far the most important use
came around in the 1800s.
Between 1790 and 1870,
the number of people living
in urban areas in America
jumped from 1 in 20 to around 1 in 4.
So to accommodate this,
people had to tack on
extra floors onto existing buildings
and courtyards would then be filled
with makeshift extensions,
effectively tightly packing all
of these buildings together.
Pretty much all these buildings
were made out of wood,
but the people inside still
cooked with open flames.
They used gas lamps, they lit candles.
So one accident
and an entire neighborhood
could go up in flames.
That reality hit New York
City in December, 1835,
when within a span of just two days,
three separate fires erupted in Manhattan.
One bystander described what
followed as "An ocean of fire
with roaring, rolling, burning waves."
By the end, a third of a mile
of Manhattan was engulfed,
destroying nearly 700 buildings
at a cost of $20 million.
That's over $730 million of today's money.
Similar catastrophes
were happening in cities
all over the world, Chicago,
London, Hamburg, Tokyo.
- [Reporter] When will this appalling rate
of destruction come to an end?
- [Gregor] The problem was
that when a building burned,
it spewed up embers into the air.
These then got carried by the wind
and landed onto other
roofs, setting them alight.
So 23 years after the
Great Fire of New York,
a 21-year-old named
Henry Ward Johns set out
to break that chain reaction
by making roofs fireproof.
But that's trickier than it sounds.
Whatever his solution was,
it had to be usable across an entire city.
So cheap and easy enough to mass produce,
durable enough to sit exposed on rooftops
baking in the summer sun,
freezing in the winter,
and most importantly, it
was not allowed to ignite
even when exposed to burning embers.
Now, Johns knew of a mineral
that was already being
spun into fireproof fabric,
but only the long fibers
were useful for thread.
The shorter ones were
actually swept aside as waste.
Johns realized those scraps
were exactly what he needed,
fireproof, tough and
most importantly, cheap.
So he set up a makeshift lab
in his basement apartment
and started experimenting.
He heated up tar in his tea
kettle, smeared that onto cloth,
and then pressed in these tiny fibers.
Then he ringed the whole thing
through his wife's brand
new clothes ringer,
and when he tested it, it
worked, it didn't burn.
In 1868, Henry Ward Johns
patented his invention,
and by 1927,
the company he built was
generating $45 million
in annual sales, more than
800 million in today's money.
Soon people were using
this fire-resistant stuff
in all kinds of building materials,
across America, consumption grew
from around 20,400 tons in 1900
to a peak of 803,000 tons in 1973.
(upbeat music)
Because of that, pretty much
every building in the US,
public or private,
commercial or residential,
used some form of this material.
During that same period,
stronger building codes,
safer heating systems
and other fire-resistant
materials were also introduced,
and it showed,
during that time, fire-related
deaths dropped around 80%.
So this material
likely helped save millions
of lives worldwide.
(lively music)
Because it couldn't be destroyed by fire,
the name the ancient Greeks
gave it, it stuck around.
They called it
inextinguishable,
or asbestos.
(bright music)
- [Presenter] Asbestos,
the remarkable mineral.
- [Gregor] By the mid 20th
century, asbestos was everywhere,
inside brake pads,
toasters, ironing boards,
hair dryers, surgical
dressings, and blankets.
You know, brewers
filtered beer through it.
One brand of toothpaste even
used it for extra polish,
the fake snow in department store windows
and in movies like "The Wizard of Oz,"
all of that's asbestos too.
- Unusual weather we're having, eh?
- [Gregor] Sorry, Dorothy.
- It was such a big deal,
Marvel even had a villain
called Asbestos Lady.
She'd set a fire to escape the police,
and she'd easily walk through it,
safe inside her asbestos bodysuit.
To feed this demand,
asbestos was pulled out of the
ground on an enormous scale.
Major mining operations
spread across Canada, Russia,
and South Africa
with global production peaking
at approximately 4.8 million
tons per year in 1977.
But the reason asbestos ended up
in so many different products is
because it's actually a
group of different minerals,
that white, fluffy stuff
we tried to burn earlier,
it's called chrysotile,
and it belongs to a mineral
family known as the serpentines.
But other types of asbestos
looked completely different.
For instance, there is also
brown asbestos known as amosite.
It forms thick fibers that
almost look like wood splinters,
strong, stable, and highly heat resistant.
So it was perfect for putting
into building materials
like cement panels.
This type belongs to a
different mineral family,
the amphiboles, here,
instead of forming sheets,
the silica tetrahedra lock
into rigid, ladder-like chains,
and amosite, iron and magnesium ions,
along with hydroxyl groups
embedded in the structure,
bind those chains together,
forming these long, needle-like fibers,
but tweak that chemistry just
slightly so that now iron
and sodium ions bind the chains,
and you get this, blue
asbestos or crocidolite.
These crystals split
easily along their length
and they create these fine flexible fibers
that are still extraordinarily strong
with tensile strengths comparable
to high grade steel wire.
This type went into
chemical-resistant insulation,
shipyards, and even filters
inside early gas masks.
Oh, and there was another use,
one that's hard to believe now.
- In this magic box I have right here
is something that was manufactured
right here in North Carolina.
They're cigarettes, produced in the 1950s,
and if you look at the filter,
you see the filters are blue, asbestos.
This is Kent with a Micronite
filter that was manufactured
with crocidolite asbestos
in the filter itself.
- So you're not only
smoking, you were smoking it
through a blue asbestos filter.
Yes, what a deal.
- Only Kent has the revolutionary
new Micronite filter
you've heard so much about.
Kent and only Kent filters best,
filters best, filters best.
(tobacco crackling)
(suspenseful music)
- [Gregor] In the early 1900s,
a young woman named Nelly
Kershaw worked in a factory
that spun asbestos fibers into threads.
Every day she breathed in the dust
that those machines threw into the air.
So by her early thirties,
she was so sick she could barely breathe.
And when she finally decided
to ask the factory for help,
they refused, they said
helping out workers
would set a dangerous precedent.
Nelly died shortly after
at the age of just 33.
Nelly's case caught the attention
of pathologist Dr. William Cook.
When he opened up her
chest, her lungs were gray
and scarred, almost blue-black,
like they had a huge internal bruise.
And when his scalpel passed
through them, they rasped.
It was like scraping against sandpaper.
The tissue was full of mineral grit,
and under the microscope
the cause was unmistakable,
asbestos fibers lodged
into the lung tissue.
- If we were to inhale some
type of an asbestos fiber,
I kind of won't think of them
as like little microscopic
straight arrows,
they kind of just shoot down
through the nose or the mouth
and move down through the trachea.
If we continue on going
down here, we get smaller
and smaller as we penetrate
deeper into the lung tissue.
And then you get into these alveolar sacs,
these asbestos fibers, they
lodge in the tissue there,
and lung secretions, enzymes,
even white blood cells,
they have a really hard
time breaking those down.
- You end up with scarring
deep inside the lungs.
In 1924, Dr. Cook published
the first medical description
of this condition, which
became known as asbestosis.
When these asbestos fibers
lodge into the lungs,
the body treats them like invaders,
specialized cells called
macrophages move in,
cells whose job it is to engulf
and digest bacteria, dust or debris.
But asbestos fibers are too
long and stiff to swallow.
It's kind of like trying to
eat a toothpick sideways.
The macrophages keep trying and failing,
and in the process, they
release inflammatory chemicals
that damage the surrounding lung tissue.
So workers breathing in
asbestos dust day after day,
accumulated more and more damage.
When doctors sent
by the British government
examined hundreds
of asbestos workers,
they found that more than 25%
already showed signs of lung disease.
And for workers with over
20 years of exposure,
that number was closer to 80%.
So in 1931, the government
officially classified asbestos
as a workplace hazard,
making it one of the
first industrial materials
to be regulated for health risks.
But the new rules only covered factories
where asbestos was manufactured.
They didn't extend to other
workers like ship builders,
miners or construction workers
who were regularly exposed
to asbestos dust.
Across the Atlantic,
things weren't much better.
There was no binding federal
asbestos rules in the States,
only a recommendation.
The US Public Health Service
suggested a temporary exposure limit
of 5 million asbestos particles
for a single cubic foot of air,
which meant that a
worker breathing normally
could inhale over 300 million
asbestos particles an hour
and still be considered within guidelines.
This became especially
problematic for shipyard workers
when World War II broke out,
ships were packed with
asbestos insulation.
So workers spent their days cutting
and fitting asbestos in
thick clouds of fibers.
And according to the
guidelines of the day,
these levels met the official definition
of safe working conditions.
In fact, asbestos was still
marketed as a magic material.
A few years earlier,
"Time" magazine actually put
Johns-Manville's president,
Lewis H. Brown on its
April 3rd, 1939 cover.
But in the early 1960s,
finally one doctor started
connecting the dots on asbestos.
Dr. Irving Selikoff was
running a small clinic
in Patterson, New Jersey,
when the local asbestos
workers Union asked if
their members could come and see him.
Before long, he'd seen multiple workers
with either severe lung scarring
or more concerningly,
an extremely rare cancer
called mesothelioma.
- A mesothelioma is strongly associated
with asbestos exposure
and is cancer of those
cells lining the inside
of the chest cavity.
And most commonly, it's
this pleural cavity.
These pleural membranes are
aligned with mesothelial cells.
Sometimes what happens is the
fibers will work their way out
of the lung tissue and directly
get into this cavity here,
and they can literally
pierce out the lungs.
- They cause constant irritation.
And over time, that can
trigger cancerous changes
in the cells that make up those linings.
Selikoff needed more data
to understand the scale
of the problem, but factory owners refused
to share medical records
from their workers with him.
So Selikoff had to get creative.
See, during World War II,
many shipyard workers employed
by the Navy underwent
federal background checks.
Thousands of these men had
been working with asbestos
to insulate ships.
So using surviving FBI
wartime personnel records,
Selikoff began tracking them down
and one by one painstakingly
pieced together
their medical histories.
What emerged wasn't a handful
of isolated tragedies,
it was a pattern,
that exposure proved
deadlier than combat itself.
8.6 out of every 1,000
servicemen were killed in action,
whereas 14 out of every
1,000 shipyard workers
later died from asbestos-related cancers.
Selikoff launched a formal investigation
into hundreds of asbestos
insulation workers,
and what he found confirmed his fears,
widespread disabling asbestosis,
dozens of cases of mesothelioma,
lung cancer rates roughly
seven times higher
than expected
and a threefold increase in
gastrointestinal cancers.
In 1964, he organized a
conference at the New York Academy
of Sciences where for the first time,
all this evidence was presented
publicly in one place,
and on the record, it marked
the moment when asbestos
stopped being seen as a
modern miracle material
and instead started being recognized
as a public health crisis.
But the asbestos industry fought back
trying to discredit Selikoff.
Industry-funded research groups came out
with papers minimizing
the risk of exposure
and framing Selikoff's
findings as overblown.
They started a coordinated
PR effort to discredit him,
trying to call him alarmist,
and starting a rumor that
he wasn't even a real doctor
just because he got his
medical degree out in Scotland.
But Selikoff kept going.
He kept publishing data on
the devastating health effects
of asbestos exposure,
he worked 18 hour days
documenting every patient
who wrote to him.
He contacted policymakers,
even world leaders,
urging them to take
action against asbestos.
- Now Selikoff, the legendary doctor
who organized this conference in the 1970s
found that intravenous drugs
were being contaminated
by asbestos filtration.
People aren't just eating it
and breathing it, they're mainlining it.
- By the 1970s, no one
could deny it any longer,
miners, factory workers,
shipyard insulators,
people who'd been exposed decades earlier
during the asbestos
boom, were now turning up
with multiple cancers in huge numbers.
- Asbestos exposure is linked
to all sorts of different cancers.
The lung tissue has
lymphatic vessels in it,
but you have 'em
throughout your whole body.
The asbestos fibers sometimes on their own
can migrate into the lymphatic vessels.
Sometimes the white
blood cells will take it
into the lymphatic system.
Once you hit the lymphatic
system, you have the potential
to go anywhere in the human body.
- [Gregor] Autopsies have found fibers
in nearly every organ in the body,
the brain, bone marrow,
spleen, intestines, pancreas,
prostate, ovaries, thyroid, and liver.
And in every tissue those fibers reach,
they set off the same chain reaction.
- I'm imagining these white
blood cells with personalities,
and they get all mad and frustrated
because they can't engulf
this asbestos fiber.
They've coined this
term called essentially,
frustrated phagocytosis.
They start releasing these things
like reactive oxygen species.
They can cause damage
to surrounding cells,
and really important is damage to DNA.
Those cells can start
dividing out of control
when they start to clump together,
and we start to call those
clumps of cells cancer.
- US courts were flooded with lawsuits
against companies like Johns-Manville.
The harm asbestos caused
was well documented.
The information was out there.
Companies should have known
their products were dangerous.
- They should know what's
reasonably available
in the public domain about
the dangers of asbestos.
If they can read asbestos patents,
they can read asbestos pathology papers.
- But the companies denied it.
What was needed was definitive evidence
that the companies knew their products
were killing their workers.
Then an attorney, Carl Ash,
noticed something strange
in the 1974 report
by this huge asbestos company
called Raybestos Manhattan.
See, in this report, the company suggested
that they had actually been
investigating health hazards
of asbestos since the 1930s.
So Ash started digging.
He filed a request for internal documents,
and at first, the company
claimed it couldn't find much.
Then unexpectedly,
Ash was handed a banker's box
stuffed full of documents,
meticulously kept by
Raybestos Manhattan's,
former president, Sumner Simpson.
Back in 1935, a journal contacted Simpson
because they wanted to write
an article about asbestosis.
Shortly after, Simpson himself reached out
to Johns-Manville's lawyer,
Vandiver Brown, saying,
"I think the less said about asbestos,
the better off we are."
To which Brown replied,
"I quite agree with you
that our interests are best served
by having asbestosis receive
the minimum of publicity."
The same papers also revealed
that in the 1930s, Raybestos
and Johns-Manville hired
an external company,
Saranac Laboratories, to do
studies of asbestos on animals.
But the companies insisted on controlling
what from those studies
will be made public.
As a letter from Vandiver points out,
"It is our further understanding
that the results will be
considered the property of those
who are advancing the required funds,
who will determine whether, to what extent
and in what manner they
shall be made public."
A clause to which Saranac
Laboratories said, "Yes."
But after their lead researcher
who was compiling all this
evidence died in 1946,
the companies agreed that
nothing should be published
that contained any objectionable material.
Objectionable meaning
any sort of indication
that asbestos causes cancer.
So when Saranac Laboratories
finished their research,
the companies took the report, edited it,
and just buried the evidence.
Here's an original copy
of that manuscript,
and you can find whole
sections just crossed out.
Other documents were even more damaging.
A Johns-Manville medical
official later testified
that up until 1971, the
company had a policy
of not telling their workers
if their physicals showed signs
of asbestosis or
asbestos-related lung cancers.
And in sworn testimony,
a witness recalled a meeting
they had in the early 1940s
with the president of Johns-Manville,
asking why they weren't
warning workers about asbestos.
As the witness recalls it, they asked,
"Do you mean to tell me
you would let them work
until they dropped dead?"
To which the president replied,
"Yes, we save a lot of money that way."
Once the Sumner Simpson papers got out,
they unlocked a new industrial Watergate.
The industry's standard, "Oh,
we didn't know," defense,
it simply fell apart.
Comparisons were made to
big tobacco's concealment
of smoking risks.
And the lawsuits surged,
each case brought new discovery
and each round of
discovery exposed a wider,
more coordinated coverup.
(files thunking)
(suspenseful music)
Ever since the word asbestosis
started showing up in medical
journals in the 1920s,
Johns-Manville went out to
secure the market around itself.
First, they acquired the
biggest rock wall company,
then they acquired a firm
holding the key patents
to calcium silicate insulation,
insulation that could be
made without asbestos.
Now, at the same time,
companies that had non asbestos insulation
were incentivized into creating
asbestos product lines.
With each acquisition or inducement,
another potential
competitor lost the ability
to denounce asbestos
and say, "Oh, we have an
asbestos-free product."
So each in turn became a member
of this conspiracy of silence.
That is how the asbestos
industry guaranteed its survival,
by ensuring no one could
speak out against it.
- [Narrator] We suggest
you consider asbestos
for the walls of your home.
- Their business decisions
and the people who make
them are businessmen.
I mean, the word morality
or moral obligation is almost non-existent
in the corporate documents.
- In 1982, Johns-Manville filed
for bankruptcy protection.
- Manville Corporation's board
of directors has determined
that the corporation should file
for reorganization under chapter
11 of the Bankruptcy Act.
- Not because they were broke,
but in a move widely seen as a way
to shield the company from a
flood of asbestos lawsuits.
Despite all the evidence against them,
Johns-Manville survived.
They continue operating to this day,
although they no longer produce asbestos.
Between 1940 and 1980,
the asbestos industry,
led by Johns-Manville,
exposed roughly 21 million
Americans to these fibers.
Asbestos related deaths
amounted to at least 8
to 10,000 people every year,
with many more suffering lifelong disease.
In 1989, the EPA issued a rule
to phase out almost all asbestos
use in the United States.
And that should have been
the end of the story.
But the industry sued immediately,
not because anyone disputed
asbestos causes cancer,
that was undeniable by this point,
but because of a legal technicality,
see, under the law,
the EPA had to prove that an outright ban
of asbestos was the only solution.
And that anything less than
that just wouldn't cut it.
This was an almost impossible feat.
Now, the industry argued
that they hadn't done that,
and unfortunately the US courts agreed.
So in 1991, they ruled that the EPA
just hadn't met this
narrow legal standard.
And with that, the asbestos
ban was dead in the water.
But by then, asbestos
had become so financially
and legally risky for the
companies that manufactured it
or used it, that its overall
use did actually decline.
Yet in the end, after
years of trying to define
and regulate asbestos,
the only thing that truly stuck around
was a definition and a narrow one.
Chrysotile and five amphiboles,
because these were the only
ones being mined, sold,
and used in factories.
But those six became the
official asbestos minerals
and anything else, no
matter how fiber-like
or potentially dangerous,
well, that doesn't count.
(suspenseful music)
- [Reporter] The FDA for
the first time in 50 years,
considering testing for
asbestos in cosmetics
and talc powder.
- [Reporter] Traces of it
have now been detected
in children's play sand.
- Thousands of people are claiming
that they developed
various forms of cancer
after years of using Johnson
and Johnson's baby powder.
- Is this all the stuff
that you've collected
over the years?
- No, it's not all of it,
but this box is full of all
the Claire's-labeled products
that I found asbestos in.
Everything little girls
could possibly want to have
their makeup in.
Like, oh, I don't know, how
about sparkly boxes, right?
- Yeah.
- And there's a cell phone.
- Yes.
- With eye shadows on it.
- Yeah.
- There's asbestos in there.
There's asbestos in the unicorn.
- It's in all of that?
- Yes.
All of these have asbestos in them.
I started seeing asbestos
fibers everywhere.
Everywhere, okay.
The eyeshadows, the blush,
they all had asbestos fibers.
Alright, wow. okay.
- What year was this?
- 2017.
- [Gregor] What?
- [Gregor] I thought it was
gonna be like 1980 or something.
What, 2017?
- Yes.
- Whoa.
- And the manufacturer came
back and said, "There's no way."
And they sponsored another laboratory
to look at the same samples.
And they said, "No, none of
this counts as asbestos."
It's all cleavage fragments,
or CPLA, clay or something like that.
And it was balderdash, right?
I called friends all across the States
and said, "Hey, do you have
a Claire's store near you?"
Can you find the sparkly box? Right.
And send it to me, pronto.
There's Claire's in all,
in all of the malls,
all across America.
And then I look further and
it's all over the world.
I mean, every mall, everywhere.
And I end up testing Claire's from Brazil
to Japan to London, I found asbestos,
- No way.
- Right.
So that turned into a huge story, right?
And now I don't think
you can buy very much
talc-based cosmetics at Claire's now,
but it was a several-years-long battle.
(suspenseful music)
These are different products
that were sold at toy stores.
Like here's the secret spy kit.
And you see there's a
fingerprint kit there, right?
And in that fingerprint kit was a powder
in which I found asbestos fibers.
Say It Ain't So Mickey Mouse crayons.
No!
- I found asbestos in those.
- And this keeps happening.
Just a couple of months ago,
around 70 schools in Australia
and New Zealand had to close down
because of the asbestos found
in children's play sand.
Out of the 60 outlets that
reported on this story,
only 24% were from right-leaning sources.
Depending on where you get your news,
this might have never crossed
your radar, which is a problem
because public health
information like this
shouldn't fall through the cracks.
And this is why we've asked Ground News
to sponsor this video.
They compile news from
outlets all over the world
into one place so that you can
easily see the partisan split
and with their color-coded layout,
it's also easy to sort your
news by factuality, ownership
and source so that you can see
how a story like this is
getting covered side by side
with all the context you need.
Take these two headlines for example,
this article from the "Herald Sun"
only talks about the fear of asbestos,
while this very high
factuality source firmly states
that asbestos was found
in decorative sand,
that difference matters,
I would like to know whether the concern
is over a mere suspicion or
actual asbestos contamination,
and that's why I find
Ground News so useful.
You get the full picture,
not just one headline
sensationalizing for clicks.
And they also have a
dedicated blind spot feed
for stories like these that are, you know,
disproportionately covered by either side
of the political spectrum,
all to help people avoid
their echo chambers.
Now, we partnered up with Ground News
because we share the same
mission, getting to the truth,
and that's why we're offering
40% off their vantage plan
at ground.news/ve.
So if you wanna support the channel,
but also want a clearer
understanding of the world,
check out that link in the description,
or you can also scan this QR code.
So I wanna thank Ground News
for sponsoring this part of the video,
and now let's go figure out
why asbestos is even getting
into all these consumer products.
Now, no one is intentionally
putting asbestos in makeup
or kids' toys,
so how did something we know is deadly
just end up everywhere?
Well, it's an unfortunate consequence
of where asbestos forms
and nowhere makes that more
clear than Libby, Montana.
- It kind of breaks my
heart to talk about it.
The mine up there is vermiculite mine.
It's about five six miles north.
- Vermiculite is a mineral
that is used in everything
from insulation to
fireproofing to potting soil.
On its own, it's harmless.
The problem was, Libby's vermiculite
formed mixed in with
affable asbestos fibers.
And the same thing happens
with other minerals we mine,
including stuff like talc.
That's how asbestos ends up in products
like the ones we saw at Sean's lab.
And the worst part, the company that owned
and operated the mine,
W.R. Grace, they knew,
they knew the ore contained asbestos.
They knew people were getting sick
and they didn't warn the town.
In fact, they tried to cover
it up for almost 30 years.
- They had hundreds of workers in there.
And of course, when the
miners would go home,
they had dust all over their clothes,
and their kids and their
wives got it and died as well.
But the doctors up around Libby,
they knew, boy did they know.
- Besides the lung disease
and cancer's long associated
with asbestos exposure,
researchers were also finding rates
of some autoimmune diseases
were nearly six times higher
than the national average.
And by the time the Libby situation
hit the headlines in 1999,
reporters documented nearly 200 deaths
in a town of fewer than 3,000.
- And it could take 20 years for it to go,
but pretty soon you have no breath at all
and you die of asphyxiation.
I could tell I'm talking on
the phone by somebody's voice,
how far along they were toward death,
because none of 'em survived.
- Finally, in 2009,
the EPA declared a public
health emergency in Libby,
calling it "The worst case
of industrial poisoning
of a community in US history."
- But Libby's just the tip of the iceberg,
- Because for decades, W.R.
Grace shipped Libby vermiculite
around the country,
and with it, deadly affable asbestos,
which ended up in millions
of homes as attic insulation.
And Grace also made a fireproof spray
that was used on the steel
frames of high-rise buildings.
By 1970, over half of
the multi-story buildings
erected in the United States
used this fireproof spray,
including the World Trade Center.
But this spray was actually
marketed as asbestos-free.
According to a later investigation
by the "New York Times,"
Grace lobbied regulators
to adopt a threshold under
which products containing less
than 1% of asbestos
would not be regulated.
Grace argued that the danger
of such small amounts had not been proved.
This became known as the
1% rule or the Grace Rule.
That decision didn't
just affect the products
from Libby's mine,
it reshaped how asbestos
was detected, regulated,
and ignored everywhere.
(building roaring)
(sirens wailing)
- [Speaker] Oh my God!
(people chattering)
- [Speaker] Look at the shadow of death!
- [Speaker] Oh my God!
- Okay, when that went down, I knew it.
I knew they had asbestos,
and so I started calling.
I said, "What do you,
how are you gonna protect people from that
'cause now that stuff's
all over the place.
You saw the dust clouds, right?"
- [Gregor] September 11th became
the largest real world test
of asbestos detection following
a single catastrophic event.
- The dust is so thick you can't see.
- When the EPA began sampling the dust
and analyzing it, they chose a
method we use back at the lab
called polarized light microscopy or PLM.
But the PLM has two major limitations.
First, it's struggles to detect asbestos
if it's less than 1% by
weight in the sample,
and second, it can only see the fibers
that are roughly longer
than about five micrometers
or wider than about a
quarter of a micrometer.
As a result, the smallest
and oftentimes the most dangerous fibers,
like the ones pulverized during
the collapse of the towers,
are difficult to detect
using just the PLM.
To reliably find these,
you need transmission
electron microscopy or TEM.
- [Sean] Where we top out
of about a thousand times
with electro, with light microscopy,
this tops out at about a million times.
But what we need to see is
just what are the finest fibers
that potentially can go into your lung.
- [Gregor] Without having used a TEM,
the EPA declared New York's air safe.
- Everything we've tested for,
which includes asbestos, lead,
and VOCs have been below
any level of concern
for the general public health.
- [Gregor] But some researchers after 911
actually did do studies with TEM.
They found asbestos levels
far above the EPA's own safety thresholds
in most of their samples.
And the report also warned that
because many of these fibers
were actually smaller than normal,
they were especially dangerous.
They posted the results
on the American Industrial
Hygiene Association website,
but within hours, their post disappeared.
Less than 24 hours later,
the researchers were notified
they been taken off the job
and were no longer
required at Ground Zero.
One former EPA chief
investigator later went on CBS
saying they believe the
agency had deliberately used
the wrong testing methods
and downplayed the danger.
- New York City directly
lied about the test results
for asbestos in air.
When they finally released
them, they doctored the result.
- We don't know if that's
true, but to be clear,
PLM is still widely
used to detect asbestos
because it's faster, it's
cheaper, it's easier to deploy.
But what we do know is two things.
First, the PLM method
was not sensitive enough
to detect whether there
were asbestos fibers
in the dust at Ground Zero.
And second, the EPA did have other,
more sensitive methods available to them.
Whatever the motives,
the result was the same.
New Yorkers were told
that the air was safe
when it really wasn't.
And as of December, 2023,
6,781 of those who have been registered
with the World Trade Center
Health Program have died
either of an illness or a cancer
linked just to their time
being around Ground Zero.
(suspenseful music)
(sirens wailing)
But even if the EPA had used the TEM,
the answer would still not be simple
because even then researchers
run into a more basic problem.
What actually counts as asbestos?
- Is there asbestos in the air?
Is there asbestos in the soil?
Is there asbestos in the water?
Is there asbestos in the body?
All of those counting
rules are based on fibers
that are not super-long,
but they're way longer than
the vast majority of say,
Libby amphibole fibers
and the vast majority of
fibers that are inhaled.
So they're not even counting those,
they're not even looking for them.
The ways that we are right now
telling people whether
they're being exposed or not
is a lie!
- [Gregor] And when longer fibers break
forming these so-called
cleavage fragments,
they don't count either.
- Yeah, there's a whole effort to say,
"Oh yeah, if it's been
broken, it's not dangerous."
But there are so many
papers out there that show
that if you put pure
cleavage fragments into mice,
they get very, very sick.
- [Gregor] This really matters
when you're in a place like this
and you realize the dust
could be considered asbestos-contaminated
under one definition,
and perfectly safe under another.
- [Researcher] Nobody would've
expected to find asbestos here.
- [Gregor] To be clear,
there were no asbestos mines in Nevada,
no industrial sites,
no history of asbestos
commercial use at all.
But geologists, Brenda Buck
and Rod Metcalf found asbestos
spread across approximately
1 million acres outside Las Vegas.
- [Rod] Geologic processes
transport these materials.
And you know, before the erosion started,
they were just in the bedrocks
along the mountain front.
Now they're in sediments down
they're, in the stream here.
- [Brenda] And the problem
with the naturally
occurring stuff like this is
it may be only a small
percentage in the rock
and even a smaller percentage in the soil,
but this stuff gets in the air.
- [Gregor] Entire communities
might be breathing it in
and getting sick without knowing.
So Brenda and Rod tried to warn people.
Back in late 2012, they
compiled all of their findings
for a presentation
at the Conference of the
Geological Society of America.
But before the conference even began,
the abstract caught the
attention of a journalist
who reported on the story,
and that's when the pushback started.
Soon the state of Nevada sent
a cease and desist letter,
and officials questioned
Brenda and Rod's methods.
- So if you go to Las Vegas,
you're gonna get exposed
to asbestos that they
didn't want that out there.
- Every time I drove into Boulder City,
there was an official
tailing me within a minute.
- The message was clear,
don't look any further.
Well, we did decide to look further.
So we drove out into the desert
to a popular off-roading spot
to test whether there really is asbestos
in the dust around Las Vegas.
Okay, I'm strapped into a dune buggy here.
I'm going to go down in that basin,
and Sean's strapped up
some dust collectors
with receivers in my breathing zone
so we can actually figure out
how much asbestos I would be inhaling
through the dust that I kick up.
(dune buggy engine spluttering)
(tires roaring)
(soft rock music)
(Gregor laughing)
Woo!
You see those donuts, huh?
- [Sean] Yeah, yeah, you were
ripping it up down there.
- [Gregor] Yeah, from a
geological point of view,
any notes?
- It rained today.
I thought about that while I was watching,
I was like, "There
might not be much dust,"
but these are the air samples
that were hanging in your
breathing room, right?
- Yes, yeah, yeah.
- And I looked at them
and the filters have some tanning on them.
- Oh, that's good.
- Which means we actually
did get some dust.
We don't know what's in it yet,
but there's something in there.
- But the original plan was for us
to actually do this at the dry lake bed
just outside Boulder City,
because this is where
people do the majority
of their off-roading,
you know, they camp, they do photo shoots,
even take their wedding photos,
except not on the day that we were there.
Okay, we're out here on the
dry lake bed, supposedly
in Las Vegas, where on the
one day that we're here,
the lake has decided not to be dry
in any sort of definition.
Oh my God.
And so what we're gonna go do is suit up,
get some samples,
and figure out how much asbestos
there really is in this stuff.
(suspenseful music)
(people softly chattering)
- [Sean] Okay.
We're gonna do a third.
Let's go out to that island.
(suspenseful music continues)
Okay.
- Okay, got the samples.
Next step, take 'em to the lab.
(car door thunks)
(suspenseful music)
- Great to see you guys again.
- Yeah, good to see you too.
Well, we are here for one thing I suppose,
like what kind of results did we get?
- Now the big reveal, drum roll please.
I did the dune buggy air samples first.
Those samples that you had on your left
and right shoulders,
I didn't find any asbestos fibers.
- Okay, well, I guess
that's a bit of a relief.
I'm glad we did the demonstration
and I'm kind of glad
we didn't find anything
because I'm pretty sure I took
my mask off at a few points.
- I've been in those shoes,
like, we didn't find anything.
Oh, but wait a minute,
I was breathing that (beep). (laughing)
- Exactly. (chuckling)
So what about the samples
in the dry lake bed?
- Ah, another drum roll.
- Okay.
- I found amphibole asbestos.
- Wow, okay.
- It's there. It is there.
I counted up a number of fibers,
the area of the filter they analyzed,
and I figured out that we had between 30
and 50 million asbestos
structures per gram of mud
that we were walking through.
- Whoa.
Just to think that we pulled
off to the side of the road,
walked what, 30 meters,
took three samples,
and all of them had these
incredibly high concentrations
of asbestos right there,
it's not like we had to go out and find.
- Right.
Very wet soil was lucky for us
because we know there's
asbestos in that soil.
Now think about the guys
that go taking their jeep across there
when it is a dry lake.
- I mean, that was our initial plan
to do the dune bugging there.
And I can't like help
but think about people drive
down that road all the time.
They must pull over,
they must go down there,
like just kick dust and rocks and-
- [Sean] We know they do. We know they do.
- And there's no sign to tell you
that there's anything
wrong with the dry lake.
It's not like we, you
know, discovered this,
this has been available data since-
- [Sean] October of 2013 is
the actual publication date
of naturally occurring asbestos,
potential for human exposure
in Southern Nevada by Brenda Buck et al.
- So 13 years we've had this data.
It's not like we'd rediscovered anything.
- And that's the other
thing that's really hard
about this science.
You need the public to be aware,
but you don't want to terrify them.
And so how do you find the right way?
- [Gregor] This will potentially be seen
by tens of millions of people.
So is there a message you want to get out?
- This is a natural hazard,
just like a lot of things in your life,
it's really good for
people to know whether
or not their house is in
a flooding zone, right?
It's really good to know
about earthquake risks.
It's really good to know about
hurricanes and tornadoes.
Well, this is just another natural hazard,
and if you have the information,
then you can make better decisions
to live a healthier life.
(gentle music)
- [Gregor] One big problem
is that asbestos in the real world
doesn't line up with how it's regulated.
Take this fiber,
it comes from a sample
of the same blue asbestos
from the site outside Las Vegas
we visited at the start of the video.
- [Sean] I think we have
two different phases,
at least of amphibole here
because if it's yellow
in this orientation,
but also blue in this orientation
in the same fiber bundle,
then we have a change in
the phase from here to here.
- [Gregor] So this one fiber
is actually two minerals.
And that complexity shows
up in its structure too,
under the electron microscope,
one side could meet the
definition of asbestos,
the other may not simply
because of its shape.
So one single fiber could fall
within one of the six named
and regulated asbestos minerals
if you look at one side,
but the other would be
completely unregulated.
Your lungs don't care about
these categories, though.
- [Narrator] The asbestos fiber,
you'll find it everywhere.
No ordinary rock, no single rock indeed,
but a group of related minerals
with characteristics in
common, but in varying degrees,
- Most experts will say,
"Asbestos isn't a mineral
or a geologic term,
it's a commercial one,"
but that's symbolics.
Why do I say that? Because it's
not just a commercial term.
We now know that asbestos can kill you.
So if we're gonna say that,
we have to define it based on
health effect, and we don't.
- [Gregor] So what are we
actually doing about it?
The system was so complex,
it was so burdensome
that our country hasn't even
been able to uphold a ban
on asbestos, a known
carcinogen that kills as many
as 10,000 Americans every year.
- [Gregor] Well, in 2016,
Congress did try to
fix this broken system.
They passed an amendment
giving the EPA new power
to evaluate and restrict
dangerous chemicals,
including asbestos.
- I think it's time to
sign the Frank R. Ladenburg
Chemical Safety for the
21st Century Act into law.
- [Gregor] But then
progress stalled, again.
Under the Trump administration,
efforts to strengthen asbestos
rules slowed dramatically.
Trump had publicly praised
asbestos for years.
- A lot of people in my
industry think asbestos
is the greatest fireproofing
material ever, ever made!
- It wasn't until 2024
that the US finally banned
chrysotile asbestos.
But this ban doesn't cover
the other five types of asbestos,
and it still allows some
manufacturers up to 12 years
to phase it out.
It doesn't address what
to do with asbestos
already in schools
and homes and other buildings,
nor does it fix any of the numerous
classification, identification,
and detection loopholes,
and it doesn't address the
asbestos in the environment.
On top of that, the EPA is
already getting sued, again.
- There have been tremendous forces
from commercial industries
to make it sound like
it's not as bad as it is,
and to find ways to allow them
to continue to use the material.
This is a sad, sad fact
of our decision-making
in our country
and other countries, is
that it's driven by money.
- But at least the United States are going
for some level of moderation.
Other countries are not that lucky.
In 2019, India imported more
than 350,000 tons of asbestos,
and it's predicted that
in the upcoming decades,
6 million people there
might develop asbestos-related diseases.
And similar things are happening
in many of the other countries in Asia.
We've actually found this website
where it looks like you
can just buy asbestos cloth
made in China, but please don't.
And all of the asbestos
that we've already mined,
even after we stop using
it, it's still out there.
Asbestos doesn't naturally
decay in the environment.
So should you be worried?
Well, having asbestos in your house
doesn't automatically
mean that it's dangerous.
If you have asbestos in your ceiling
and you don't drill into it,
you're probably gonna be fine.
Asbestos is an issue if
the particles go airborne,
but who knows which house has asbestos,
where all of that asbestos is,
who's gonna take care of it and how?
So a lot of the answers to these questions
just don't exist yet.
But if you're worried about
asbestos exposure for yourself,
check out the links that
we've put in the description.
I think a big part of the problem is
that people assume
asbestos is a solved issue.
And I'll be the first to admit,
I fell for that line of thinking.
Here's the ending I
wrote for our PFAS video.
- We've been here before
with lead gasoline, Freon
and asbestos, and each
time we did the research
and made the right decision
to phase these chemicals out.
- Yeah, I was completely oblivious.
- We will look back at our history
and what do we do with tobacco?
Everybody was smoking, right?
It would be improper for me
to not offer an ashtray
even if I wasn't a smoker back in the day.
And all the scientists working
for the big cigarette companies said,
"Why, tobacco never hurt anybody."
But because of the outcry
and the recognition that
smoking causes disease,
everybody knows someone who died
because of cigarettes, right?
Now, you might find out that
asbestos-related diseases
has touched you in some way,
you don't even know yet.
I didn't know my grandfather
died because of asbestos,
that my father is dying
more likely than not
because of asbestos.
Did I know that when I started
looking at asbestos
under a microscope, no.
Did I know that when I changed
the brakes on the Jeeps
that I ran around in, no.
Did I know that when I ran around
through asbestos-containing dust, no.
Now I do.
- Pretty much every scientist
and journalist we spoke to for this video
said the same thing.
This is a hard story to get out there.
They've faced economic
pressure, political pressure,
the research got buried,
and some people even
received death threats
for reporting on the story.
It is an uncomfortable topic,
but I think it's these
uncomfortable topics
that matter the most,
that have the potential
to do the most good,
yet they are also the ones
that are the most uncomfortable to watch.
So I really appreciate you
for sticking around to the end
and facing the truth,
making yourself aware
and becoming part of the solution.
So perhaps now more than
ever, thank you for watching.
(screen chiming)
(suspenseful music)